<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-16T16:49:41+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Performative Nuance</title><subtitle>The blog of Ada Cable</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Depression, Hope, Genocide, Horror, Action.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/09/01/Depression-hope-Genocide-Horror-Action.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Depression, Hope, Genocide, Horror, Action." /><published>2022-09-01T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-01T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/09/01/Depression-hope-Genocide-Horror-Action</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/09/01/Depression-hope-Genocide-Horror-Action.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m in a bad depression- maybe coming out of it, maybe not. 90% of the time I say I’m coming out of depression I get hit over the head by it really badly.</p>

<p>I still, mostly, have hope. I think I’m probably the most hopeful person I know- When my depression gets really bad, it sometimes disappears, normally for a night or two.</p>

<p>The rest of the time, I’m hopeful. Not in the same way most people do- I think the next century is going to contain a lot of genocides. They fill me with dread and horror.</p>

<p>Honestly, I’ve spent so long with the horror of genocide it’s become both the dominant thought I have and a background to my thinking- but this is because there are <em>so many of them</em> and they’re <em>so big</em>.</p>

<p>I see the genocides that are coming as both a horror that keeps me up at night and also as fact- They are going to happen. I don’t have hope of avoiding them.</p>

<p>And that’s why I have hope. Because hope is about the things you can change, not the things you can’t. Differentiating between the two is a key part of actually doing hope.</p>

<p>Accepting genocides are going to happen is not the same thing as accepting genocide.</p>

<p>I will fight these genocides to the best of my ability- I know this is true. Some small fraction of these genocides will be prevented because I acted. Some small fraction already have. So will many many others(probably you), and we will win.</p>

<p>What is important is while I am certain that the genocides will happen, I am also certain that some of those that may happen will be prevented.</p>

<p>Every horror of the 21st century is still undecided- We decide which, how horrific, and how many.</p>

<p>I have a belief that we can make good choices, that we have agency, even the tiniest amount, that we can make a difference between better and worse.</p>

<p>This is based on a knowledge that every system, every genocide, every empire, has been made up of people who have made these choices.</p>

<p>Every persons choice has been shaped by their situation, but it has also shaped their and others situations in turn.</p>

<p>It is up to us to choose, but we cannot choose if we believe every one can be prevented, or if we act like failure to prevent one is a unique sin, and every horror we prevent is a sufficient victory, we will not be able to act.</p>

<p>And action is the key.</p>

<p>Seeing the horrors of the 21st century as a result of peoples actions rather than as abstract impossible sins gives me my reliable hope.</p>

<p>There is no way around the 21st century, we have to go through it. We also had to go through the 20th century. And the 19th. They all had preventable genocides and all could have had more.</p>

<p>For every holocaust there’s a united nations, for every coup there’s a revolution, and for every preventable death, there’s a saved life.</p>

<p>They don’t even each other out, but the point isn’t to achieve “ok” any more than it’s to achieve “perfect”.</p>

<p>The point isn’t to achieve, it’s to do.</p>

<p>The 20th century wasn’t an “terrible” or “excellent” or “ok” performance- it just happened. The 21st will happen too, and all that matters within it is action.</p>

<p>To see it otherwise requires a belief in something external, like the teacher grading a report card “they did ok this century but we’d really like to see some improvement in the empire department and a couple less death camps” often accompanied by a belief that you can pass or fail- “Sadly your species failed to achieve full communism this century and you’re going to have to retake it”.</p>

<p>And the desire to create this external metric on which we can be graded always involves leaving things out- The tankies would like us to forget death camps and remember literacy rates, the Anarchists would like you to remember the freedom of our communes and forget their size and temporality, the colonialists forget plantations and remember railways, the billionaires forget sweatshops and remember global gross domestic product.</p>

<p>Horrors are coming. This is an inevitability, and has always been. If it was not the climate crisis it would be something else- for the 19th and 20th centuraries it was modernity-enabled imperial slaughter. In the 22nd it will be a new, seemingly unique horror.</p>

<p>My hope isn’t a grading system I believe we can attain a passing grade on, my hope is a knowledge that we will take action.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Depression" /><category term="Hope" /><category term="Genocide" /><category term="The horrors" /><category term="Action" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m in a bad depression- maybe coming out of it, maybe not. 90% of the time I say I’m coming out of depression I get hit over the head by it really badly.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Write to think</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/22/write-to-think.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Write to think" /><published>2022-05-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/22/write-to-think</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/22/write-to-think.html"><![CDATA[<p>Been missing writing here so, here’s a reminder to my self.</p>

<p>The reason I write is to think: For myself and also to help the people who read what I’m writing, and to think together with them.</p>

<p>A lot of the time I approach writing as a way of being right- raise the funds, recruit the people, talk the person out of doing , etc.</p>

<p>Writing to think is different. It’s about clarifying your thoughts, checking them for inconsistencies, concentrating them and showing them to other people for them to ingest and disagree with and think against and through and with.</p>

<p>Writing to think is messy and collaborative and incredibly fucking scary because it’s about being wrong.</p>

<p>If you’re writing to think you’re hoping you’re wrong all the way through, and you move on even though you know it’s wrong and if you’re fucking stupid like me you show it to other people even though you know it’s wrong.</p>

<p>And if you’re at all subject to disposability that’s especially fucking stupid because you’re explicitly giving people with power over you and who hate you the tools to destroy you.</p>

<p>Anyway when you write the wrong thing to think you get other people to tell you it’s wrong and hopefully they’re mostly in good faith ish and then you’re thinking together.</p>

<p>Writing to persuade is different(it’s writing to be right), and is less good at making you think. Doing it all the time destroys your ability to learn(lol tankies). Writing to persuade and instruct has value, but it’s not what this blog is for. That comes later.</p>

<p>Write to be wrong, and write to think, don’t write to persuade as your default.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Blog" /><category term="Navel gazing" /><category term="Writing" /><category term="God ada write something useful not this" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Been missing writing here so, here’s a reminder to my self.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s not an IFAK and we should stop calling them that.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/It's-not-an-IFAK.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s not an IFAK and we should stop calling them that." /><published>2022-04-22T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/It&apos;s-not-an-IFAK</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/It&apos;s-not-an-IFAK.html"><![CDATA[<p>The US military(and many other organisations and people influenced by them) talk a lot about a thing called an IFAK, or individual first aid kit. It consists of trauma supplies, for people to use on you, or for you to use on yourself- Generally a couple of standard tourniquets, some chest seals, some gauze(normally haemostatic, sigh), and some gloves. Contents beyond that differ, but that’s most of it.</p>

<p>The thing is, the individual first aid kit isn’t individual. If you’re an individual in a situation like that, it probably doesn’t matter if you have a tourniquet on you- You’re gonna die when your leg gets blown off, because someone is going to shoot you while you’re lying on the floor trying to apply the tourniqet.</p>

<p>Which makes sense, because it’s designed to be used at least with a buddy, and probably with a fireteam.</p>

<p>The IFAK is designed to be used by people who are not you- The doctrine is, if someone gets a traumatic injury, you get them to cover and take one of their tourniquets from their body and use it on them.</p>

<p>That way, you have all your own trauma kit left on you, so that when you get injured, it’s still there and someone else can use it on you.</p>

<p>The IFAK means that the designated “medic” in the group doesn’t have to carry twice as many tourniquets as they’re responsible for(just a few spares), along with all the other kit that’s in an IFAK, and it means equipment is always present at the scene of the injury.</p>

<p>It’s a way of distributing the load across the team, making sure it’s always near to where the injury is.</p>

<p>The IFAK isn’t about the individual, it’s about making sure that the collective is resilient against one(or more) of it’s members taking a traumatic injury.</p>

<p>Not because it’ll immediately make the injured person able to function as part of that collective, but because people are a lot less afraid of getting shot if they know their buddy will drag them out and a helicopter is coming to pick them up and that following that there’s an entire system designed to look after them.</p>

<p>That’s why all military medicine exists: The state has no compassion, just a need for better soldiers.</p>

<p>The IFAK is just the part of the system that tricks soldiers into dying for the state that’s carried closest to the body.</p>

<p>Seen this way, it’s obvious why the US military call it an IFAK- It appeals to the soldiers sense of individualism, of self reliance. It’s presence becomes a talisman, a physical reminder with weight and presence, that if you’re shot there’s a good chance you’ll, if not be ok, then at least be alive.</p>

<p>This also makes it obvious why it’s spread so far as a meme into the Cop world, and the associated Gun/EDC/prepper/etc communities: It’s all about being an individual who can be rambo prepared, or occasionally about taking individual responsibility for carrying a firearm(in the more left/libertarian spaces).</p>

<p>The IFAK combines the mystique and eroticism of military culture(for non veterans) with the rugged individualism narrative of the prepared frontiersman, and the appeal of a massive haemorrhage as a clear problem with a simple solution, to create a powerful talisman which can be used to ward off the bad things(much like a concealed carry pistol is to an actually trained friendship group).</p>

<p>The IFAK is a mostly symbol of “care”, completely stripped of the context for which it was evolved, and turned into a talisman of either macho preparedness, or individualist responsibility.</p>

<p>As leftists and collectivist types, we don’t want to reproduce these connotations- If we’re thinking about individual first aid kits, it’s a sign we’re not organising, because we’re alone, or at least that we’re pretending we’re organising alone in the same way the US military does.</p>

<p>If we’re going to be carrying similar things(and carrying kit has it’s own value- we should be doing so), we should call it what it is: It’s a <em>Distributed</em> first aid kit. It’s a set of things we carry among ourselves, as a group, to care for one another. Maybe it’s including sweets for blood sugar, mental health meds, or naloxone.</p>

<p>When we’re aware that it’s a thing we carry collectively, it makes it easier to bulk buy and organise, it makes more sense that it’s (semi-)standardised rather than based on personal preferences, and it makes us think about things which aren’t trauma but still need immediate aid.</p>

<p>We’re not trying to make sure we, as individuals, are prepared for trauma, we’re trying to equip a group of people with skills and equipment to care for one another against the risks we’re likley to face collectivley.</p>

<p>Shifting the way with think about it in those terms means we relate to it differently, and build it differently, and organise differently.</p>

<p>So let’s call them DFAKs, shall we, and have a think about how to build them differently together?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Kit" /><category term="Carrying" /><category term="First aid" /><category term="IFAK" /><category term="DFAK" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The US military(and many other organisations and people influenced by them) talk a lot about a thing called an IFAK, or individual first aid kit. It consists of trauma supplies, for people to use on you, or for you to use on yourself- Generally a couple of standard tourniquets, some chest seals, some gauze(normally haemostatic, sigh), and some gloves. Contents beyond that differ, but that’s most of it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Things that help win wars, in approximate order of importance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/21/Things-that-help-win-wars,-in-aproximate-order-of-importance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things that help win wars, in approximate order of importance" /><published>2022-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-21T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/21/Things-that-help-win-wars,-in-aproximate-order-of-importance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/21/Things-that-help-win-wars,-in-aproximate-order-of-importance.html"><![CDATA[<ol>
  <li>Economic base</li>
  <li>Logistics</li>
  <li>Geography</li>
  <li>Doctrine</li>
  <li>Training of strategists</li>
  <li>Propaganda</li>
  <li>Morale</li>
  <li>Maintenance</li>
  <li>Standardisation</li>
  <li>Intelligence</li>
  <li>Training of front line units</li>
  <li>Medical care</li>
  <li>Food</li>
  <li>Air superiority</li>
  <li>Artillery</li>
  <li>Small arms</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Addressed to all the leftists who think owning one single pistol is cool" /><category term="Conflict" /><category term="Strategy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Economic base Logistics Geography Doctrine Training of strategists Propaganda Morale Maintenance Standardisation Intelligence Training of front line units Medical care Food Air superiority Artillery Small arms]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Disorientation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/19/Disorientation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disorientation" /><published>2022-04-19T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-19T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/19/Disorientation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/19/Disorientation.html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a model of decision making called the OODA loop- If you’re friends with me I’ve probably explained it to you at least once, but it goes something like this: When making a decision you Observe the world around you, Orient yourself within it, Decide what to do, and then Act- And then Observe all over again.</p>

<p>It was developed in the cold war, as a way of understanding air combat- The idea(mostly correct) being that if a pilot could iterate through the loop faster, they could outthink their enemy, and win the fight- Thus aircraft were designed to facilitate faster decision making and reaction, sharper turning and better vision, as opposed to higher speed or more powerful weaponry.</p>

<p>I’m gonna use it to talk about PTSD(another cold war model) instead.</p>

<p>My experience of PTSD<a href="#fn:1">1</a> is that it shorts out parts of the loop- PTSD means you go from observation straight to somewhere else- Often action, but also the very act of observing can fuck with your ability to observe further, trapping you Observing a flashback.</p>

<p>PTSD is a set of well worn tracks in the mind in a body that you follow without a choice- You’ve done it so many times, that you just skip the middle OD of the loop, and leap straight to action- Your phone rings, and the body knows what that means: Cortisol and adrenalin time, push the disassociation so you don’t freeze. Answer it.</p>

<p>The well worn tracks are useful- Like disassociation, they’re tools to help you survive. It becomes a problem when they go to the wrong places- When you’re no longer in the situation that wore those tracks in your mind, and you don’t need to go to those places right the fuck now, and it’s better that you stop and decide which track to go down.</p>

<h2 id="re-oreitnation">Re-Oreitnation</h2>

<p>Overall: Maintaining the ability to orient yourself in stressful situations isn’t possible alone. No-one is a natural at it, and no-one can do it alone. It’s why you train orientation- In first aid, we call it the danger step, and we attach rituals to it: Putting gloves on.</p>

<p>One of the people who taught me is a doctor who’s got experience on call for cardiac arrests in a hospital setting. It’s literally a life and death situation- Seconds matter, and if you spend any time in a hospital you can see how reaction to these (“code blues” in NHS speak, maybe elsewhere too) is built into the architecture- Wards have carts, with all the same equipment in all the same layout, maintained and charged<a href="#fn:3">2</a> and ready to(literally) roll when one of these is called. When you hear it over the tannoy, you step to the side of the corridor so everyone who’s actually involved in the incident can get there.</p>

<p>This doctor taught me, that, when one of those is called, even if they’re stood right next to the patient, they go over to the box of gloves on the wall, think about what’s happening, pull on a pair of gloves, then walk back to the patient.</p>

<p>Their well worn path now goes to a place which makes them think- A little ritual to make space, to think about yourself in the relation to everything going on around you.</p>

<p>Orientation: Thinking about yourself in context.</p>

<p>Gloves are good, because they’re about looking after yourself in the middle of everything- They prompt the next thing to do, which is to think about danger, and then you’re going through the rest of your acronym- A well worn path, hopefully, but it’s not a single path, it’s a decision tree, a framework of well defined tiny little loops.</p>

<p>Fast action, sure, but slightly slower and correct action.</p>

<p>I used to argue training is equivalent to traumatising people in the right way, with minimal harm.</p>

<p>I was mostly wrong: Trauma wears the paths directly to action. Training does this Ocasionally<a href="#fn:4">3</a>, but training is mostly about maintaining orientation when everything is exploding around you. It’s about embedding a set of paths, not a single one.</p>

<p>In a sense, it’s it’s own orientation: When confronted with a situation, training provides and answer as to who you are in that situation: When I’m in a situation involving injuries or illness, I’m someone who pulls out a pair of gloves, puts them on, and then follows my accident procedure.</p>

<p>A part of my PTSD recovery has been people training me, and me training myself, to put the Orient step back into my life- I’m literally rebuilding my sense of self, reenforcing it to allow me to know who I am and what I do when it’s all exploding.</p>

<p>The world is getting to a place where we experience more exploding, every day. We need to learn to Orient better, which means pausing for the half a second it takes to put gloves on, even when it feels like someone’s about to die as a result.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Or trauma or whatever: I think I’m broadly Post most of the things that caused this batch- undoubtedly there’s more coming, but I’m doing my best to avoid it. <a href="#fnref:1">↩</a></li>
  <li>With breakaway chargers, so you don’t have to think about unplugging it. <a href="#fnref:3">↩</a></li>
  <li>Most of the cases I can think of involve highly specific immanent or occurring violence, and normally running. <a href="#fnref:4">↩</a></li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There’s a model of decision making called the OODA loop- If you’re friends with me I’ve probably explained it to you at least once, but it goes something like this: When making a decision you Observe the world around you, Orient yourself within it, Decide what to do, and then Act- And then Observe all over again.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">formative</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/17/formatiive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="formative" /><published>2022-04-17T01:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-17T01:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/17/formatiive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/17/formatiive.html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my formative memories is walking through a art museum, in Moscow. There’s gorky park, full of removed Lenin heads, which you probably know about. And in that park is the most incredible museum. I walked in and saw a small exhibit- A mid 2000s computer, and on a flopy next to it, a copy of a worm- I think stuxnet. In retrospect, geopolitically charged. Held together as one artistic exhibit, it opened my eyes to what art could be- The Arab spring was springing, or just beginning to stop, I remember because a few months later I logged on to my google reader in a cafe in ulan bator, and caught up with the news. It was a long way away.</p>

<p>Beyond the atrium, I walked through a history of modern Russian art- Modernists and exiles bouncing off the bauhaus, glorious visions of a predictable and perfect future, of potential, and then through galleries of soviet realism- Odes to the peasant and the tractor. And then at the end, was an exhibit by a young artist- I don’t know who, or what- I remember energy, opening, I remember protests and police and rage. Contrast and saturation pumped right up, and him jittery in skinny jeans in a small gallery off the main run of this quiet gallery, excited and at the start of his career. Full of potential.</p>

<p>It is a start of the person who was ada- She’s about to travel across a giant fucking continent and probably not really speak english to other people for nearly a month. It’s a lot. She reads Lessig, and sees him speak a year later, rides the Beijing subway, and discovers affordances, and mostly realises she’s a she and is probably not going to do something like this for a long time.</p>

<p>Everything is opening.</p>

<p>It feels like a long fucking time ago. It is.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Personal," /><category term="Russia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of my formative memories is walking through a art museum, in Moscow. There’s gorky park, full of removed Lenin heads, which you probably know about. And in that park is the most incredible museum. I walked in and saw a small exhibit- A mid 2000s computer, and on a flopy next to it, a copy of a worm- I think stuxnet. In retrospect, geopolitically charged. Held together as one artistic exhibit, it opened my eyes to what art could be- The Arab spring was springing, or just beginning to stop, I remember because a few months later I logged on to my google reader in a cafe in ulan bator, and caught up with the news. It was a long way away.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Training tourniquets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/20/Training-Tourniquets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Training tourniquets" /><published>2022-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/20/Training-Tourniquets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/20/Training-Tourniquets.html"><![CDATA[<p>The tourniquet is something I’ve tried quite hard to avoid in my life- Not just in the “avoiding a massive haemorrhage” sense, but in the “avoiding tactical medicine” sense.</p>

<p>Recently I spent nearly £2500 of other peoples donations on CAT tourniquets, and shipped them into Kyiv for civilian prehospital providers. After doing that, I think it’s time to think differently about tourniquets in UK trainings and protocols.</p>

<p>I work in situations where massive haemorrhages are an if, not a when- I’ve not dealt with them, but people in queercare have.</p>

<p>But I’ve chosen not to emphaise tourniquets, or put a lot of infrastructure into making sure people have them.</p>

<p>I carry one, sometimes, on spikier demos and similar, and I know some other people have bought them for themselves.</p>

<p>But we don’t focus on them, and tell people not to focus on them- They’re just the thing that comes after direct pressure when you’re dealing with a massive haemorrhage. You can make one with a triangular bandage and your shears.</p>

<p>This runs counter to a lot of the noise you’ll hear, especially from Americans. Americans love tourniquets- The more the better, and if you can have chest seals and hemostatic gauze too, that’s great. What do you mean activated charcoal and something to help with blood sugar?</p>

<p>Carrying tourniquets is dominant in the aesthetics and discourse of layperson prehospital care, as much as carrying milk for tear gas is.</p>

<p>But the focus on an object rather than a technique has always been a problem- People obsess over them, and avoid learning the skills they need to deal with most dangerous situations they encounter- Which is probably deescalation.</p>

<p>For the last 50 years in UK street medicine, and community care, even adjusting for our updated knowledge on their efficacy and reduced risks, keeping them tucked away was the right call.</p>

<p>I think it’s time to bring them out a bit more- Not make them the core part of our training they are in military medicine, but train with dedicated tourniquets.</p>

<p>Why?</p>

<p>Because that makes sense in warzones and other dangerous areas, and it’s becoming more likely that people we train will end up there. Probably the uk will become more of one.</p>

<p>There are a lot of uk civilians all around ukraine right now.</p>

<p>Some of whom are leftists, many of whom are working unaffiliated and without proper medical training for the situation. The fact that Ukraine isn’t surrounded by a set of hostile states(like syria) and you don’t need to get in an aircraft to get there(with it’s attendant “why are you carrying so much outdoors gear”<a href="#fn:1">1</a>) makes this a bigger problem. Couple it with large Ukrainian diasporas and a sense of solidarity among the eastern European community, and you have a recipe for a lot of people from our communities in dangerous places without training.</p>

<p>(There are racial effects at play here: I think I’m adjusting for them, and obv people from the UK have been fighting and doing aid elsewhere forever- Across the Middle Aast and Africa to start with, I suspect a chunk of SE Asia, but I don’t know the conflicts there as well. But all of them have a lot more friction to enter than Ukraine. )</p>

<p>Warzones like this will get more logistically proximate, and our protests and riots will get spikier.</p>

<p>The gay bashing will get worse and so will white supremacist violence.</p>

<p>We need to be ahead of events when we’re building infrastructure to deal with those events.</p>

<p>We train now not so the people will be able to deploy a CAT on a protest tomorrow.</p>

<p>We train now so in 10 years they’ll be able to open a box of them we’ve left above a shop somewhere, or whom someone fundraised for entirely independently, and be able to tell their friends how to use them.</p>

<p>We train now so the buddy pair that’s traveling as a walking manifest and trainer with a #QCWR shipment knows what to do when the very NGO aid convoy gets hit by an IED from some proxy who doesn’t really listen to their imperial trainers.</p>

<p>We train now so in ten years it’s not new and scary, but instinctive and normal.</p>

<p>So yeah. This isn’t a post about whether you should carry a tourniquet. If you do it’s almost certainly a sign you’ve got either misplaced priorities or a fetish. The latter is fine, the former is dangerous.</p>

<p>It’s a post about whether we should build an infrastructure that has, at it’s endpoints far from here and now, people using tourniquets.</p>

<p>We should do that. We’ll be grateful.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Assumes basic levels of competence. For many it will be “why are you carrying so much tactical gear”? <a href="#fnref:1">↩</a></li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ukraine" /><category term="first aid" /><category term="queercare" /><category term="tourniquets" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The tourniquet is something I’ve tried quite hard to avoid in my life- Not just in the “avoiding a massive haemorrhage” sense, but in the “avoiding tactical medicine” sense.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What am I trying to do here</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/What-am-I-trying-to-do-here.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What am I trying to do here" /><published>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/What-am-I-trying-to-do-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/What-am-I-trying-to-do-here.html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog, quite obviously, exists. It’s been around for a bit but I’ve actually posted here a lot more the past two weeks, partially as a result of meds changes and then re-writing the site one afternoon to be nice and simple and easy to post to from IAwriter.</p>

<p>Right now it’s an attempt to build something of a public daily writing practice, because I think that will help me think better: Twitter is my normal outlet for this stuff and it has all sorts of affordances which make it terrible for thinking with, and also terrible for communicating anything about complex events. The tight feedback loop of the likes and the retweets always calls though- Especially when something needs attention or funds.</p>

<p>I also want it to be a place for documenting failures and successes, doing debreifs in public so others can learn: I’m not sure I’m ready to do too much of that publicly, given I’m only just recovering from precarity, and similar attempts going bad.</p>

<p>My writing is still quire reactive. I’m talking about things on the news, and worse, things on twitter. I’d like to change that.</p>

<p>Soon, hopefully, I think it will be a place to begin doing longer term thinking. I’ve got a lot of experiences to process, and a lot of thoughts that people keep getting as intense rants, which are better suited for longer writing and being more easy to hold alongside each other than twitter threads.</p>

<p>I want to live up to the URL as well: Every medium I can communicate in right now has absolutely no space for nuance or complexity. I think thinking that engages seriously with the other side of an argument, and with context, is sorely needed.</p>

<p>I think it’s a little offputting when I write something like overpressure which is simply trying to help people understand something, and not argue for a specific policy. I think it’s also helpful when I write something like the <a href="/2022/02/24/Practical-steps-to-help-ukrainian-people-right.html#ukrainian-organisations-in-the-uk">ukraine solidarity guide</a> which comes from a perspective which is little heard(refugee admissions were…not really on the table at that point).</p>

<p>So then a second generation outcome I want, beyond helping me think, is to help other people think. The culture of blogging was incredibly inspiring to me as a tiny person when I first encountered it, and I think it inspired a lot of thought. I don’t hope to inspire, tbqh, but I think if I can provide context and remind people that there are positions beyond theirs and the one they’re most used to arguing against, that’s good.</p>

<p>Part of that is showing people how I’m thinking, and not just the conclusions. It’s going to be messy. And probably badly spelt. And capitalised. like this post tbqh.</p>

<p>Mostly, right now, it’s a place to put text on the internet- it’s ok if it stays there.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Meta" /><category term="blogging" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog, quite obviously, exists. It’s been around for a bit but I’ve actually posted here a lot more the past two weeks, partially as a result of meds changes and then re-writing the site one afternoon to be nice and simple and easy to post to from IAwriter.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Overpressure</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/Overpressure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overpressure" /><published>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/Overpressure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/Overpressure.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my attempt at an explainer of what a thermobaric weapon, a vacuum bomb, or a fuel-air explosive is, what their history is, why they are awful and their use should be condemned on a different scale to other warfare, similar to nuclear bombs.</p>

<p><strong>Please consider simply taking my word that these should not exist, and not finding out why I think this.</strong></p>

<p>Through the last years of the cold war, both sides had thoroughly covered their borders with a deep and strong network of bunkers- Both a comprehensive line, and stretching far back along any line of advance.</p>

<p>This made any kind of advance by a tank column untenable- These bunkers stretched deep into the hillside, much like the famous cave networks of Afghanistan, and were essentially impossible to penetrate with conventional bombs, and no-one wanted to push the nuclear button.</p>

<p>So both sides developed the same solution: Thermobaric weapons. These weapons spray fuel or explosive in a mist across a wide area, and then ignite it with a small conventional explosive. The result is a massive detonation for relatively little weight and size in the warhead- A fireball of massive proportions, but more importantly, a shockwave.</p>

<p>If you cause a shockwave in an open field, the shockwave dissipates quite quickly. Most weapons rely on shrapnel or fire to cause damage beyond this radius.</p>

<p>If you cause a shockwave at the entrance to a tunnel, it travels down the tunnel, and down any tunnels that connect to it, and through most doors, without really getting the chance to dissipate- There’s no-where for it to go, compared to an open field.</p>

<p>If you launch a thermobaric weapon against a bunker, the shockwave rips through the bunker. It’s not a loud noise, or a soft ripple of air- it destroys everything in it’s path. It bounces between walls and down corridors and off blast doors.</p>

<p>When the blast clears, the size of the explosion has normally deprived the surrounding area of oxygen, and it takes a long time to return to areas which may have avoided the shockwave through distance or behind blast doors.</p>

<p>Thermobaric weapons partially neutralise bunkers, certainly enough to get close and storm them with minimal resistance.</p>

<p>US and NATO doctrine emphasises air support and precision strikes- This seems like a contradiction in terms with a weapon like this, but dropping it close to a bunker entrance is important.</p>

<p>The US used thermobaric bombs in Afghanistan, when cave systems fortified by fighters were deemed too costly to storm with American troops.</p>

<p>US marines used shoulder launched versions against fortified buildings in Afganistan.</p>

<p>British helicopters also launched similar sized thermobaric missiles in Afghanistan.</p>

<p>Russian doctrine still values precision strikes but places more emphasis on scale and the number of explosions.</p>

<p>The Russians have built several different ways of deploying thermobaric weapons, but the one under discussion in Ukraine is the TOS-1(or TOS-1a- the differences are invisible externally and it doesn’t matter for this post).</p>

<p>The TOS-1, or “heavy flamethrower” is a multiple launch rocket system. It is a set of 30 rockets, loaded on tubes on top of a chassis. The chassis of the TOS-1 is a tank chassis, because it’s designed to travel with the tanks at the spearhead of an invasion force, and target bunkers.</p>

<p>When fired it covers an area 200 by 400 meters in thermobaric explosions. Nothing in it or close to it survives. You don’t need to know where the bunker entrance is too well, or spend too much time worrying. Just point approximately and shoot.</p>

<p>The cold war ended, The bunkers are largely mothballed, and while Russia retains nuclear power it is an economic backwater and cannot muster sufficient logistical support to contest a conventional war against NATO.</p>

<p>This weapon remains.</p>

<p>It were sold to lots of countries who Russia thought had a good chance of hurting the US. Iraq had some- the Iraqi national army fired them at a building filled with ISIS fighters, in the middle of a city.</p>

<p>US planes circled overhead and “advisors” from the remainder of the coalition sat with the troops when they did this.</p>

<p>They launched one rocket at the building, and it destroyed it.</p>

<p>It was a horror, and a crime, and should never have happened.</p>

<p>Syria was sold some, and in the early civil war they used them, along with nerve agents, in cities occupied by rebels, at their full force.</p>

<p>A city, in many ways, resembles a lot of small bunkers with no blast doors. The explosion rips through windows and doors. Frequently the walls are shattered too, and the entire building collapses.</p>

<p>The state of Syria used these weapons and pointed them at areas of cities populated by rebels and civilians, and they fired them.</p>

<p>In 1996, Chechnya was no longer part of the soviet union, and opted not to join the Russian state. Between 1994 and 1996 the Russian state fought a committed and bloody war against a Chechen Guerrilla force. They were defeated by heavy urban fighting and mobile raiding forces harassing their logistics. A ceasefire was signed.</p>

<p>In 1999, Russian backed Chechens began an insurgency against the Chechen state, as a prelude to a full scale invasion by Russia. In Grozny, the capital, where urban fighting had previously stymied the Russian advance and led to their defeat, different tactics were used. Russian rockets constantly attacked the city, including using cluster munitions.</p>

<p>The siege lasted two months.</p>

<p>The TOS-1 was at the forefront of this, and was responsible for levelling massive chunks of the city.</p>

<p>In 2003 the UN described Grozny as the most destroyed city on earth. It was essentially flattened.</p>

<p>More than 5000 civilians died.</p>

<p>The Ukrainian army is currently fighting an effective war harassing Russian supply chains with highly mobile units and the Russian army has so far almost religiously avoided urban close combat, preferring to encircle cities instead.</p>

<p>The Ukrainian state has issued arms to it’s citizenry and encouraged resistance. Fighting for the cities with tanks and infantry would be a basically impossible task.</p>

<p>The TOS-1 has been seen in staging areas all around Ukraine.</p>

<p>Examples were seen leaving staging areas in Belgrood, north of the Ukrainian city of Kharkiv, earlier today.</p>

<p>The siege of Kharkiv has seen cluster munitions used on civilian areas.</p>

<p>Today the Ukrainian ambassador to the UN stated that thermobaric weapons had been used.</p>

<p>The most vulnerable people of Ukraine are hiding deep in their cities metros- Enclosed, hard walled spaces perfect for sheltering from conventional bombs and rockets.</p>

<p>I have not described what happens to people when they’re hit by the shockwaves. The purpose of this post is to help you understand these weapons, why they were made then, who uses them now, how they use them now, and why this should never happen. I don’t think a description beyond what you can see above is necessary for you to do that.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Ukraine" /><category term="War" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is my attempt at an explainer of what a thermobaric weapon, a vacuum bomb, or a fuel-air explosive is, what their history is, why they are awful and their use should be condemned on a different scale to other warfare, similar to nuclear bombs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Things that are equivalent</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/Things-that-are-equivalent.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things that are equivalent" /><published>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/Things-that-are-equivalent</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/01/Things-that-are-equivalent.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the prelude to a longer post discussing the differing counterinsurgency doctrines of US, UK and Russian forces, and their roots in empire, and their horrors.</p>

<p>However, for now, this is a post about whether it’s a good idea to compare the US and UK use of thermobaric weapons with the russian use of them(I don’t think it is) and if that’s not a good comparison, what is?</p>

<p>If you don’t know what a thermobaric weapon is, especially with respect to the one deployed by Russia in Ukraine right now: I wrote <a href="/2022/03/01/Overpressure.html">this</a>, which attempts to explain their horror clearly.</p>

<h2 id="us-and-uk-weapons-in-use">US and UK weapons in use</h2>

<p>The Thermobaric warhead on the missile the UK has fired in cities weighs 10kg, and has a blast which is lethal over a space effectively the size of a house. It is accurate to within a meter or so of its aim point.</p>

<p>The Thermobaric warhead on the rocket used by the US in urban areas has a weight of about 2kg. It has a smaller blast than the UK missile. It’s accuracy depends significantly on the distance it’s used at, but it’s probably within a few meters of it’s aim point.</p>

<p>Either of these could easily kill civilians unintentionally, and it’s very possible these weapons were used to target civilians intentionally. I consider it unlikely- they are not efficient or easily covered up ways of doing this, which the US and UK soldiers prefer, and they are supposed to be used on targets unlikely to have nearby civilians in.</p>

<p>War crimes in Iraq and Afghanistan looked different. However, it is not especially well documented, and is plausible.</p>

<p>The thermobaric bomb dropped by the US on a military<a href="#fn:1">1</a> held cave complex in a rural area weighed about 910kg. Its blast in open air would be comparatively small, but it would certainly kill everyone in a large bunker or cave system.</p>

<h2 id="russian-weapons-in-use">Russian weapons in use</h2>

<p>The Russian weapon under discussion is a multiple launch rocket system with 24 217kg rockets. Not all of these rockets are warhead- How much is unknown. Firing one causes a series of blasts in an area over 200 by 400m, and destroys any thing in enclosed spaces in these areas. They also destroy many buildings within these areas.</p>

<p>Documented uses of them in the second Chechen war on areas of Grozny held by Chechen forces, and which I’m certain contained civilians- no area of a city 200m by 400m wide does not contain some civilians. Realistically, it contained many civilians and was not used(and is impossible to use) in a discriminating manner.</p>

<p>The horror of Grozny is not all a result of thermobaric weapons- conventional artillery, cluster munitions, and well trained highly motivated nationalist fighters with a willingness to commit abundant war crimes all played a part.</p>

<p>But its role is significant and distinctive.</p>

<h2 id="comparison">Comparison</h2>

<p>The weapons above all use the same explosive mechanism. They are comparable in that.</p>

<p>The weapons above all should not exist: This is a binary condition, and they all meet it.</p>

<p>Some weapons above are more indiscriminate than others- The US rocketry is less accurate than the UK missiles, but has a smaller warhead. The US bomb is similar in total warhead weight to the Russian rockets- But it’s a point explosion, and very accurate, rather than a blanket.</p>

<p>I would suggest that in effects, the Russian weapon is more comparable to the following than it is to their use by the US/UK:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The US use of nuclear weapons on Hiroshima and Nagasaki.</li>
  <li>The firebombing of Dresden by the US and UK.</li>
  <li>The use of Napalm on Vietnamese villages by the US.</li>
  <li>The use of agent orange and other defoliants by the US on Vietnam, and by the British on what is now Malaysia.</li>
  <li>The British use of concentration camps in Kenya and Malaysia, and many other colonies.</li>
  <li>The UK/US/Iraqi army/Coalition tactics in Mosul(though, this is more tenuous- AFAICT there were proportionally fewer civilians on the ground)</li>
</ul>

<p>The US and UK are not wanting for war crimes or horrors they have enacted. The fact that the US and UK have moved away from destroying cities in their entirety is not reflective of a shift to a “kinder” or less harmful doctrine- simply a more insidious one which achieves the same aims more effectively and cheaply.</p>

<p>I think comparing the horrors of US and UK use of thermobarics with the horrors of Russian use of thermobarics because they carry the superficial resemblance in the type of explosive ends up minimising the suffering of the Chechen people in Grozny and the likely immanent suffering of the Ukrainian people.</p>

<p>Comparing simply on the use of thermobarics is often a superficial engagement with the suffering enacted by imperial powers in a rush to get quick dunks in.</p>

<ol>
  <li>It was held by AQ and Taliban fighters. It very possibly contained people working on logistics and infrastructure, as well as cooks and cleaners who did not carry arms. I think applying a similar lens to it as would be applied to a military base is reasonable. <a href="#fnref:1">↩</a></li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Ukraine" /><category term="Russia" /><category term="Imperialism" /><category term="Colonialism" /><category term="Thermobaric weapons" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the prelude to a longer post discussing the differing counterinsurgency doctrines of US, UK and Russian forces, and their roots in empire, and their horrors.]]></summary></entry></feed>